All right, ready to go. Welcome to the second פרק perek? *Perek*.
The second פרק perek *Perek*, דף כז *Daf Chaf Zayin*,
the second פרק perek *Perek* continues with the laws of שחיטה shechitah
*Shechitah*. It starts where I think maybe many of us would have
hoped or expected that the first פרק *Perek* would have started, which
talks directly about the act of שחיטה shachting *Shechitah* and what is
required and how much has to be cut and so
on, whereas the first פרק *Perek*, as we know, started with more
like the פסולים psulim *Psulim* or the כשרים *Kasherim*, if you want
to say that, הכל כשרים *Ha-kol Kasherim*. But who שחט shachts. *shechts*,
what type of object, what time of day? Anyway, here we finally
turn to the act of שחיטה shachting *Shechitah* itself, but interestingly where
you might expect then that we're going to be very technical, the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* certainly uses it as an opportunity for a lot
of interesting abstract and conceptual questions as we will see. So let's
begin now with the second פרק *Perek*, כז עמוד א *Chaf Zayin
Amud Aleph*, top of the דף *Daf*. השוחט Hashocheit, אחד בעוף ושנים
בבהמה *Ha-shochet echad ba-of u-shnayim ba-beheimah*, so one who slaughters one סימן
siman, *Siman*, right, trachea or esophagus in birds, or two in the
animals—I mean birds are animals, but we'll just say animals, more technically
I guess we'd say mammals. שחיטתו כשרה shechitato ksheirah, *Shechitato kesherah*, the
שחיטה shechitah *Shechitah* is valid. ורובו של אחד כמהו *V-rubo shel echad
kamo-hu*, the majority of one counts; you don't have to do a
full trachea, full esophagus, a majority is sufficient, as we've discussed before
and we'll continue to discuss again. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda אומר *Rabbi
Yehuda omer*, whether
these
are לכתחילה lechatchilah *Le-chat-chila* or בדיעבד *B-di-avad* will also be discussed in
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, right? Whether לכתחילה lechatchilah *Le-chat-chila* you should שחט
shacht *shecht* two by a bird, whether לכתחילה lechatchilah *Le-chat-chila* you should
שחט shachted *shecht* a full amount, not just the רוב rov. *Rov*,
these will all be discussed. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda. אומר *Rabbi Yehuda
omer*, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda *Rabbi Yehuda* says, עד שישחוט את הורידין
*Ad she-yishchot et ha-vridim*, you also have to שחט shacht *shecht*—interesting use
of the verb and we'll talk about that—you have to שחט shacht?
*shecht* the arteries, the, I believe presumably, the carotid artery, which is
the main artery in the neck which gets out the blood,
in both the animal and the bird. Well, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
will actually interestingly limit it to the bird, not to the animal.
We might have thought the animal has all that blood, you really
need to work at getting it out. We'll see in the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara*. The interesting question for us to ask is: does he
consider this part of the act of שחיטה shechitah. *Shechitah*, which is
implied by the verb עד שישחוט *Ad she-yishchot*, also implied by the
point that it sounds like you're not יוצא *Yotze*, it's not a
valid שחיטה shachting *Shechitah* unless you cut the carotid artery, or is
he saying, no, maybe the שחיטה shechitah *Shechitah* is good but I've
got another problem, I don't want, you need to get the blood
out, you can't eat the meat with the blood, so in order
to address some other problem. It certainly does not sound like the
latter, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say it's the
latter. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda* not about the act of שחיטה shechitah. *Shechitah* but about
a separate problem of getting out the blood. Okay, but again in
the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* you do not get that sense, and the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is aware of that. Okay, so he says you
also have to cut the carotid artery. Now I say that presumably
it's the carotid artery because the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* later speaks about
it being one side of the neck, although there is a רש״י
*Rashi* that talks about them being on both sides of the neck.
So, but simply
it is presumably the carotid artery. I assume that's what... Do we
have a picture in that book? Can you hand me that book
over there? I'm sure we have a very nice graphic picture of
that. You have your book too? I did not bring my book
today, unfortunately. Oh my god, look at all these gorgeous full-color pictures.
Oh my god!
Joe, this is your book?
Wow!
Great cartoon pictures at the end. What am I saying, this only—oh,
this is only חלק ב *Chelek Bet*, right?
Where does this start?
Doesn't start from the beginning. Oh
wait, it looks like it does. Hold on. Oh no, it just
starts from פה *Poh* here. Okay, oh my god, you can look
at the trachea and the esophagus of a sheep or an ox.
Oh my god! Yeah, that's good stuff.
Okay, anyway, you want to
know what it looks like. I have no idea.
Oh, so he says yes, so actually he has it as the
jugular vein. There's the trachea, esophagus, and the jugular vein. So can
somebody help me? What's the difference between the jugular vein and carotid?
Well, one is a vein, one is an artery. So I guess
there are two
veins on each side? Are there?
Here it says right jugular vein and רש״י *Rashi* does speak about
there being one on each side, the jugular vein. Okay, I guess
ורידין veridin? *Vridim* sounds like veins.
And here they have carotid arteries which it seems that there are
two,
right? They're saying carotid arteries, there must be two.
The two ורידין *Vridim* referred to here are the carotid arteries. Make
up your mind! Are they the carotid arteries or are they the
jugular veins? Okay,
all right, I will have to look into that more. The two
pictures contradict themselves. But it does say there are two carotid arteries.
All right, anyway, so they are obviously a major blood vessel in
the neck and that is his point. I will try to get
that back to you more. We actually, anyway, it's not even an
academic point because we actually פסק *pasken* like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
*Rabbi Yehuda*. So it's got to be... So I will get back
to you on exactly the ID. identity of these ורידים, vridim, whether
they
are the jugular veins,
okay, I'll get back to you on the specifics. Let's keep on
going. חצי אחד בעוף ואחד וחצי בבהמה. Chatzi echad ba'of ve'echad v'chatzi
bab'hemah.
If one did exactly half, not a majority, exactly half of the
bird, and one or one and a half in a בהמה, behemah,
שחיטתו פסולה, shechitato pesulah, it's invalid. So the גמרא Gemara is of
course going to say that that's obvious, we just said you needed
a majority. Why do you have to tell me again that if
you did only half it's not good? Part of the חידוש chiddush
is the fact that it says if you did one and a
half in a בהמה, behemah, which means you did a full one
plus a half of the other. So the total amount of סימנים
simanim you cut was 1.5, whereas if you only do the majority
of each, .6 and .6, you only need 1.2. So nevertheless, although
you've actually cut more in this case, since you've only cut half
of the second and not a majority of the second, it is
still invalid. רוב אחד בעוף ורוב שנים בבהמה, Rov echad ba'of verov
shnayim bab'hemah, and now it seems to be totally repeating itself. The
majority of one in a bird and the majority of two in
a animal, שחיטתו כשרה, the שחיטה shechitah is valid. Okay, so here's
the basic point about you need the majority of one and the
majority of two, and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you need the
ורידים, which are either the carotid artery or the jugular vein, to
be- to be clarified hopefully tomorrow. Let's take a look at the
גמרא. Gemara השוחט, the גמרא Gemara, says if one שחט. shachted So
דיעבד di'eved in- it sounds like only דיעבד di'eved it's good, לכתחילה
lechatchilah no. But it sounds like לכתחילה lechatchilah you've done something wrong.
Now notice, the first line in the משנה Mishnah. doesn't even say
a majority, it says if you שחט shacht one in a bird
and two in a בהמה. behemah. So what's דיעבד di'eved about that?
You שחט shacht the complete two. So that's what the גמרא Gemara
wants to know. So maybe you could say there's a דיעבד di'eved
by שחיטה shechitah one in a bird, that maybe ideally you should
שחט shacht both in a bird. That we could imagine. But what
could be the דיעבד di'eved by שחיטה shchita the two full סימנים
simanim in a בהמה, behemah, the- both the קנה kaneh and the
ושט. weshet. Oh well maybe. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. So the גמרא Gemara says, לכתחילה lechatchilah no. It sounds like
לכתחילה Lechatchilah you do not do it correctly. שנים בבהמה לכתחילה לא?
Shnayim bab'hemah lechatchilah lo? Two full סימנים simanim in a בהמה behemah
לכתחילה lechatchilah. is no good? עד כמה לשחוט ואזיל? Ad kamah lishchot
ve'azeil? How far- how much more do you want him to שחט?
shacht He שחט shacht both the קנה kaneh and the ושט. weshet.
So you could have said, right, maybe לכתחילה Lechatchilah like רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. גמרא Gemara says,
איבעית אימא אחד בעוף, Iba'it eima echad ba'of, one way of saying
it is that yes, it implies that it's only דיעבד di'eved because
of the bird, meaning ideally you should שחט shacht even two by
a bird. That's one possibility, which raises an interesting question: is that
really true? לכתחילה lechatchilah we want you to שחט shacht two by
the bird? So that's one possible read of the משנה. Mishnah. ואיבעית
אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, if you want you could say, ארובו של אחד
כמהו. A'rubo shel echad k'mohu. You're right, it's not going on the
first line of the משנה. Mishnah First line is you did everything
you had to do, one by a bird, two by a בהמה.
behemah. But it's the second line of the משנה that says it's
enough to do a majority. That there the point is that's not
לכתחילה. lechatchilah לכתחילה lechatchilah you should do the full סימן, siman דיעבד
di'eved a majority is okay. And רש"י Rashi says the reason for
that is presumably because if we let you- not because there's conceptually
some problem with that, but because, you know, sometimes it's very close:
what's the majority? Was it only 50%? Was it 49%? So to
be safer that you're really doing the majority, we ask you לכתחילה
lechatchilah to do all of it. Now רש"י Rashi speaks of that
way as like a rabbinic concern. I would want to put out
there a point that we have discussed before and will come up
again, when this idea that a majority is enough, how do we
conceptualize that? Do we conceptualize that as your basic obligation is to
שחט shachted 51%? Or do we say no, your basic obligation is
to שחט shecht the entire thing, but 51% counts as if it's
the entire thing? רובו של אחד כמהו. Rubo shel echad k'mohu. It
sounds like fundamentally it's supposed to be the entire, 51% is as
if it's the entire. One of the implications of that is, as
we said, let's say there's a פסול psul in the last 49%.
You didn't do 51%, you did the whole thing, but at the
last- in the last 49% you did something wrong: שהייה, shehiyah, דרסה,
derasah, etc. Does that matter? Or is the שחיטה shchita done when
you do 51%?
Or is the 51% a stand-in for the full amount? And when
you did the full amount, the full amount is the שחיטה. shchita.
So here it could also be relevant to the question of לכתחילה
lechatchilah should you do it all. If the 51% is a stand-in
for the entire thing, it's still saying the- the principle is you
should שחט the entire thing. We'll allow 51% to count as if
you've done it. So that would explain why the גמרא Gemara is
saying here that לכתחילה you're supposed to do all of it. Okay,
so here the גמרא Gemara has one possible לכתחילה of שחיטה shchita
both סימנים simanim by a bird, which is interesting: why that should
be important? But then the other one, which obviously seems to be
more of a focus of the גמרא, Gemara is לכתחילה doing the
full סימן siman? not just the רוב. Is that a גזירה? gezeirah?
You might not do enough? Or is that conceptually that you really
are supposed to be doing the full amount? Rabbi? Yes.
Do we ever determine what they really do today in terms of
a bird?
I will- I will have to ask. As you can see from
numerous comments that I have made, I have never learned שחיטה shchita.
and do not really know the practice- the practical practice of שחיטה.
shchita So, you know, I- I know שחיטה shchita from גמרא חולין.
Gemara Chullin. So we need somebody that actually has done it. You
know, some of my students have been learning שחיטה shechita and one
is actually- really finished. So maybe I can arrange for him to
come in one morning and talk to us a little bit about
some of these details. I think that would be helpful. Okay.
You know, it's actually quite funny that we today sort of, you
know, what things that would seem to us a little more modern
or scientific etc. were already done by ראשונים Rishonim of already some
of the ראשוני ספרד Rishonei Spharad more than אשכנז. Ashkenaz.
So for example when they had a problem with the גמרא Gemara
they
would check manuscripts, you know, compare different manuscripts. But anyway the reason
I bring it in is because when they were learning חולין Chullin
there are stories about how the ראב"ד Raavad would actually bring into
the ישיבה Yeshiva like animal parts, you know, some of the organs
and show the students like what it was being referred to. You
know for us we can learn an entire year we have these
books, but you know entire year of מסכת חולין Masechet Chullin and
never actually you know really grapple with the reality. So I will
try to address that. Okay, let's keep on going. What was Rivka's
point yesterday? What? It was
Rivka's point yesterday. Yeah, that is true. אמר רב כהנא. Amar Rav
Kahana. רב כהנא Rav Kahana says: מניין לשחיטה שהיא מן הצוואר? Minayin
lishchita shehi min hatzavar? Now we're going to move on to how
do we know about all these ideas of שחיטה shechita anyway? What
does it talk about it in the תורה? Torah? So the גמרא
Gemara is not asking the basic question of how do you know
שחיטה shechita. at all, that there's an idea of ritual slaughter. We've
seen before that the גמרא Gemara understands that when the תורה Torah
uses the word וזבחת, vezavachta, that means a ritual act of שחיטה.
shechita But here it is asking how do we know that it
is the neck. Now that could be excluding two other possibilities. I
mean not two only two but basically one question is how do
you know it's not any other part of the animal like, you
know, stabbing it in the heart or cutting it in you know
stabbing it in the back? How do you know it's the neck?
And within the neck how do you know it's the throat? How
do you know it's the front of the neck and not the
back of the neck? The reason I say the second is that's
how תוספות Tosafot understands some of what's going on is identifying which
part of the neck meaning the throat as opposed to the neck
as opposed to another part. Let's take a look. אמר רב כהנא
מניין לשחיטה שהיא מן הצוואר. Amar Rav Kahana Minayin lishchita shehi min
hatzavar. How do you know שחיטה shechita takes place at the neck
or the throat? שנאמר, Shenemar, the verse says: ושחט את בן הבקר.
Veshachat et ben habakar. This is by the קרבן. korban. He shall
slaughter the calf. So where do you see from there that it's
the neck? So we're going to do a little play on words.
ממקום ששח חטאהו. Mimakom sheshach chata'ehu. From where it ששח, shesach, where
it bows down, there חטאהו chata'ehu which here we're reading to mean
either cleanse it meaning somehow like finish it off or חטאהו chata'ehu
means like purify it. The word לחטא lechate can mean to purify,
a little ironically but that's actually because לחטא lechate means to cleanse.
So meaning to cleanse it also means to purify. So purify to
make something טהור tahor is somewhat analogous to making something כשר. kasher.
So they're reading the word from where it bends make it pure
or make it כשר. kasher. Now where does it bend? If you
ever look at a cow, no, but you look at a cow,
right? A standard cow, its neck is angled down. Right? So that's
the part of its body that is at an incline is the
neck. So it's true and I can't it could crouch but the
point is, you know, that's where it inclines if you want is
the neck. So that's where you do the שחיטה. shechita ממאי דהאי
חטאהו לישנא דדכויי הוא. Mimai dehai chata'ehu lishana dechikuyahu. Where do you
know this word of חטאהו chata'ehu means to cleanse? You know,
or רש"י Rashi has a גרסא girsa of לישנא דאכשורי הוא lishana
de'achshureihu which means to validate, make it כשר. kasher. Okay, cleanse would
mean to remove the blood. Although ironically of course the act of
שחיטה shechitah? is not about removing the blood, right? The act of
שחיטה shechitah by severing the trachea and the esophagus is not really
focused on the blood. But anyway how do you know that this
word חטאהו chata'ehu either means to cleanse it of the blood or
to validate, make it כשר? kasher? דכתיב וחטא את הבית. Dechtiv vechite
et habayit. He shall this is about the מצורע metzora how you
purify the house. So again either you cleanse the house or you
purify the house. So those words can be applied analogously to making
the meat כשר. kasher. ואיבעית אימא מהכא, Ve'iba'it eima mehacha, if you
want from the following verse: תחטאני באזוב ואטהר. Techate'eni be'ezov ve'etaher. Purify
me or cleanse me with the אזוב, ezov, with the hyssop. This
is like the sprinkling of the ashes of the פרה אדומה Parah
Adumah and I will become pure. Okay so somehow we have the
word חטאהו chata'ehu meaning cleanse, purify, somehow meaning make the animal כשר
kasher and שח sach meaning incline where the neck is.
So this must be an אסמכתא asmachta because it really sounds like
it.
Let's see where the גמרא Gemara ends up. ואימא מזנבו? Ve'eima miznavo?
How about the tail? Right? The tail also is always inclined downwards.
So the גמרא Gemara says ah, so the גמרא Gemara says שח
מכלל שזקוף. sach miklal shezakuf. No, inclined, bent, meaning that there are
times when it is you know when it is straight, when it
is erect and the tail is always hanging down. ואינן, Ve'inan, so
the גמרא Gemara says והא שח ועומד הוא vehasach ve'omed hu is
always is always hanging down. ואימא מאזנו, Ve'eima me'ozno, maybe the ear?
Because an animal can apparently you know twitch its ear and bend
down bend its ear. I don't know I can't do that but
apparently cows can, bend their ear. So maybe the ear, which it
does bend sometimes? So the גמרא Gemara says בעינן דם הנפש וליכא.
be'inan dam hanefesh veleka. No, we know from other places by קרבנות,
korbanot, you know the תורה Torah emphasizes that what you do when
you slaughter the קרבן korban is you get the soul the blood
of the soul because it speaks about getting the blood and the
blood is where the soul resides. So therefore obviously if you just
cut it in the ear you're not going to get the blood
of the soul to come out. You also won't kill it. ואימא
ve'eima so the גמרא Gemara says so so what, let's say דקרב
ואזיל עד דם הנפש, dekarav va'azil ad dam hanefesh, you start at
the ear and you keep on cutting till you actually you know
hit an important vein or something and get the blood to come
out, but maybe and the blood of the soul, but maybe you
start at the ear.
The גמרא Gemara says and two, and in addition, now actually here's
a major question about what the word is. I'm going to actually
read this like תוספות, Tosafot, who instead of the word ותו vethu
says ולטעמיך, vileta'ameich, which means fits sort of better. So here it's
being challenged because this word is being said I don't know which
part of the animal I'm talking about, you can't really get it
from the verse. So the גמרא Gemara says back, again our version
is ותו vethu and in addition, but תוספות Tosafot has the גרסא
girsa of ולטעמיך. vileta'ameich. So what according to you that you're challenging
me, you know, let me ask you a general question. שהיא הדרוסה
חלדה הגרמה ועיקור מנלן? shehi haderusa chalada hagrama ve'ikur minalan? How you
know you're never going to learn all laws of שחיטה shechitah, from
the פסוק. pasuk. Where do you know all of the classic criteria
of שחיטה shechitah that you you know or the פסולים psulim? that
you can't pause, that you can't put pressure, that you can't burrow
you know sort of start in the middle, that you can't do
it in the wrong place, that you can't uproot you know have
an uprooted סימן? siman, Where do you know all those laws? There's
no פסוק, pasuk, אלא גמרא, ela gemara, we know it from tradition.
So שחיטה נמי מן הצוואר נמי גמרא. shechita nami min hatzavar nami
gemara. Okay, so basic answer is, as Michael's saying is, you got
me, you're right, you know, I'm not going to get it from
the פסוק, pasuk, you know, obviously this פסוק pasuk is doesn't sound
like it's what it means anyway, and number two is you can't
really get it to tell you neck, you could wind up saying
the other part. So you're right, I know the idea of neck
from where we know any all other laws of שחיטה. shechitah We
know it from tradition. Okay, so then what? וקרא למאי אתא? vekra
lemai ata? But interestingly, rather than just saying forget the whole פסוק
pasuk it's אסמכתא, asmachta, the גמרא gemara, doesn't want to give it
up. So what is the פסוק pasuk telling us? דלא לשוויה גיסטרא,
delo leshavei gistera,
not to make it something severed into two. What does this mean?
So רש"י Rashi says I'm going to well, so רש"י Rashi says
what it means is when you שחט from the throat, don't continue
all the way to the back and sever the backbone. Why not?
Now a the question is why not? And two, where do you
get that from the פסוק? pasuk? All the פסוק pasuk says is
you know whatever we read the פסוק pasuk where it bows down
whatever how do you know not, so רש"י Rashi says well what
it means is שחט until you make it כשר kasher וחטאהו vechate'ahu
no more. All right, but anyway it's a weird idea, why would
I think why are you not allowed to go all the way
to the back? תוספות Tosafot says, and this is again the way
predominantly תוספות Tosafot reads this סוגיא, sugya, the way תוספות Tosafot reads
the סוגיא sugya is that it starts trying to prove neck, in
the end because there're going to be other דרשות drashot as well,
it's going to admit it can't prove neck. We have to learn
that from tradition. But what it is going to say is once
we know neck, I'll use the פסוק pasuk to tell me throat,
not back of the neck. How is that's what it means, not
גיסטרא. gistera. Don't go from the back and meaning like you like
sever its head, cut off its head, go you know cut the
neck bone, go from the throat, from the front of the neck.
How do I know that? Because since it says where it
now again I don't get how he learns this, since it says
where it inclines, that's the throat and not the neck. I don't
get it, if it inclines it's bending also its neck bone. So
I'm not exactly sure in the end of the day how תוספות
Tosafot gets that, I guess maybe he would say that the idea
of וחטאהו vechate'ahu if it means cleanse it of the blood, so
the place that you would first focus on getting the blood would
be from the front, from the back you know it takes longer
to get to the things that will cut the blood.
Right, so that's going to be the first focus of the cutting,
not the blood. Right, so that's going to
be the first focus of the cutting, not the blood.
Anyway what? Right, so the גמרא Gemara sounds like no, sometimes it's
erect, sometimes it bends. So the גמרא Gemara does not mean that
it's naturally bent, that was the problem the גמרא Gemara had with
the tail. So I don't exactly get it in terms of תוספות,
Tosafot, it might be because of the emphasis of the blood or
cleansing from the blood, but for תוספות Tosafot the point at the
end is yes we know from tradition neck, we know from the
פסוק pasuk throat. Okay, the front of the throat and somehow maybe
because of emphasis on blood we know the throat. Again I do
want to point out the irony and this will get us back
to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is that שחיטה shechitah is not about
the blood. שחיטה shechitah. is about the trachea and esophagus and in
theory if you could maybe do a very precision שחיטה shechitah and
just cut the trachea and esophagus you could do it without getting
any blood out. Right? I mean it would die out of asphyxiation,
right, not out of loss of blood. So it's very interesting according
to one read of רש"י Rashi and what we're suggesting for תוספות
Tosafot is that the פסוק pasuk is telling you emphasizing get out
the blood. רבי יהודה speaks about the blood but that's not how
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma position is. Okay, so that's one דרשה.
drasha. Now we're going to do another דרשה drasha which will be
very similarly.
Okay so let's take a look. Hold on let me just double
check.
Yeah. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this. רב
יימר אמר אמר קרא Rav Yeimar amar amar kra the verse says
וזבחת vezavachta again another verse for
slaughter. From, again. Here it's explicit. Notice again the bizarre emphasis on
blood. Where it flows, חתהו, chateihu, you shall cut it. Before we
said חטהו chateihu with a ט. tet. Here it's saying חתהו chateihu
with a ת, tav, which the גמרא Gemara is saying means cut
it. So first of all, מאי משמע דהאי חתהו לישנא דמתבר
הוא? mai mashma de-hai chateihu lishna de-mitbar hu? How do you know
the word חתהו chateihu means to break it, you know, to sever
it? דכתיב, de-chtiv, because the verse says אל תירא ואל תחת, al
tira ve-al techas, do not be afraid and do not tremble. So
here, dropping the first, so they understand the word חתית chitiyos means
to tremble, so חתהו chateihu means but to tremble, to shake is
like also to be, you know, to like, they're reading also to
like, let's, you know, the fear, don't let the fear break you.
So they're reading the word חתהו chateihu to mean to break. So
where the blood flows from, there you should break it, and that
would mean the neck. Again, a fascinating emphasis on blood. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says, ואימא מחוטמו, ve-eima mi-chotmo,
maybe its nose? Things flow out of its nose, you know, mucus
flows from its nose, so maybe that's also a place of flow?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, זב על ידי חיתוי בעינן. zav
al yedei chitui bayinan. We need something that flows because you're cutting
it, והאי, ve-hai, your nose, זב מאליו הוא, zav me-eilav hu, flows
without being cut, right? Just, you know, mucus flows from your nose.
Okay, ואימא מלבו, ve-eima mi-libo, alright, but if you want to get
blood flowing, maybe you should stab it in the heart or cut
it by the heart? Who says cut it by the neck? וטו,
ve-tu, and in addition, a תוספות Tosafot would say לטעמיך, le-tameich, so
okay, so you're right. I can't, I can't prove throat. Maybe it
means heart. But שהיא דריסה חלדה הגרמה ועיקור מנלן? she-hi derisah chaladah
hagramah ve-ikkur menalan? How do you know any of the details of
שחיטה? shechitah. אלא, ella, what do we say? גמרא, Gemara it's a
tradition. שחיטה מן הצואר נמי גמרא. Shechitah min ha-tzavar nami gemara. Alright,
so you're right. I give up, you know, you got me. So
the idea of that the neck is also not from a פסוק,
pasuk, it's a tradition. But still, what do we do with the
פסוק? pasuk? דקרא למאי אתא, de-kra le-mai ata, what's the פסוק pasuk
coming? דלא לשויה גיסטרא, delo leshaveih gistra,
not to sever it in two, which again for תוספות Tosafot means
not from the back of the neck, from the throat. If the
emphasis is the flow and blood, get it where you're going to
get directly to the flow of the blood, get it from the
throat, don't get it from the back of the neck. So again,
for תוספות Tosafot consistently the point of all this is we wind
up admitting that the idea of throat is not, cannot be learned
from the verse, that we know from tradition like so many other
laws, but what we get from the verse is the throat rather
than the back of the neck.
It's based on
a still very bizarre דרשה. drasha. But again, for me what's even
more fascinating is that now both דרשות drashot that are telling me
throat and not back of the neck are because of the emphasis
on blood, right? And according to the רבנן Rabbanan it's not about
blood at all. Okay, and nevertheless we're being told where to focus
on based on where the blood is going to come out. So
that is again quite fascinating. Let's take a look at yet another
דרשה. drasha.
What do the רבנן Rabbanan say about that?
Well, they say that the reason, because you went back to the
very beginning, רבי יהודה says that while you're שוחט shocheting it you
also have to cut like the either the jugular vein or the
carotid artery, we're trying to figure out which, but anyway, a major
blood vessel. What?
The חוט השדרה chut ha-shidrah or vein?
So how come in the next picture it calls them the carotid
arteries, ורידין? ורידי הצואר? veridei ha-tzavar? הצואר? ha-tzavar?
Okay anyway, whatever. So anyway, let's, whatever they are, so רבי יהודה
says you have to cut the major blood vessel and get out
the blood while you're שוחט. shocheting. But the רבנן Rabbanan say no,
just the trachea and the esophagus. If you can focus just on
the trachea and the esophagus, you can have very little blood come
out and have the animal die of asphyxiation, right? So it is
the act of שחיטה shechitah. is not about getting the blood out.
Now the גמרא Gemara will say that when it does come to
קרבנות, korbanot, and at least to one of these פסוקים, psukim, it
was talking about a קרבן, korban, there obviously you have to get
out the blood because you're trying to do the blood as part
of the ritual. But nevertheless, as a valid act of שחיטה, shechitah
it's not the, the focus is not on blood. And nevertheless here
the דרשות drashot all point to the location where the blood is
going to come out. So again I, you know, I don't know
exactly what to do with that. It works nicely according to רבי
יהודה that focus is on the blood as well. But even the
גמרא Gemara interestingly is even going to sort of bracket, you know,
even say even רבי יהודה's point is not so much about שחיטה
shechting as it is about just how do you get out the,
you know, making sure you don't have blood when you have to
כשר kasher the meat. So the שחיטה shechitah is not really about
blood although these דרשות drashot are focused very much on blood. So
let's see now where the גמרא Gemara goes. דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא,
De-bei Rabbi Yishmael tana, from the house of רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
we taught,
ושחט, ve-shachat, you shall slaughter. אל תקרי ושחט, Al tikrei ve-shachat, don't
read it you shall slaughter, אלא וסחט. ella ve-sachat. Now סחט sachat
could mean squeeze and again mean squeeze out the blood, but again
the גמרא Gemara's is not going to finish here. Similar like the
type of thing we did before, ממקום שסח mi-makom she-sach where the
animal talks from its, you know, throat or mouth or whatever, חתהו,
chateihu, that's where you should cleanse. So again, so here right, obviously
conceptually it's not about talking, it's just pointing to the location. So
the location is where the part of the animal... animal that does
the talking, which presumably is, well, that's what my גמרא Gemara asks.
ואימא מלשונה, ve'eima milshonah, maybe you cut its tongue, that's more where
it talks than its throat. ביותר דם הנפש נפקא. beyoter dam hanefesh
nafka. So no, בעינן דם הנפש וליכא, be'inan dam hanefesh veleka, obviously
we know in the context of קרבנות, korbanot, that the שחיטה shechitah
gets out the blood of the soul. That won't come out by
just cutting the tongue. It also won't kill it. So the גמרא
Gemara says ואימא דכרי ואזיל עד דם הנפש, ve'eima decharei ve'azil ad
dam hanefesh, maybe you start at the tongue and you keep on
cutting until you get this blood of the soul to come out,
until you actually do kill it. וטו, vetu, or תוספות Tosafot says
ותימא, veteima,
so now again, we've got you. How do you know it really
means throat? Maybe it means, you know, maybe it means a what
do you call it, tongue or some other body part? So המרש"א
Hamarsha says, okay, שהיא דרשה לחוד וגמרא והיכא מיניה, she'hi d'rashah lachud
ve'gemara ve'heicha minei, how do you know anything? How do you know
all the פסולים? אלא גמרא, ela Gemara, it's all tradition. שחיטה מן
הצואר נמי גמרא, shechitah min hatzavar nami Gemara, so the idea of
the throat is also tradition. Okay, וקרא למה אתא, vekra lamah ata,
so what are you going to do with the פסוק? pasuk? Why
do you need the פסוק pasuk of where it talks? דלא לשוייה
גיסטרא, delo leshavyei gistra, not to sever it in two. It's again
תוספות Tosafot means, it's the throat and not the back of the
neck. Again, because the talking part, you know, comes from your throat.
If you start at the back of the neck, you're not starting
with the talking part. Now, finally, according to this דרשה, drashah, although
it's not conceptually about talking, but at least it's pointing you to
what is the real סימנין, simanin, because the סימנים, simanim, the trachea
is that part of the body that does the talking, so not
the esophagus. Okay, but at least this דרשה drashah is not focusing
on blood, this דרשה drashah is focusing on that body part which
is central to the act of שחיטה. shechitah Okay, so you have
these various דרשות, drashot, they do feel a lot like אסמכתות, asmachtot,
in the end for you know a lot of it is dictated
by just tradition of what we know. But it is interesting to
realize what sort of focus the גמרא Gemara, is using the פסוקים
psukim for.
Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues to make these דרשות, drashot, but
does it in a slightly different, excuse the pun, vein than it's
been doing until now. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, okay,
ותנא מייתי לה מהכא. ve'tanna mayti lah mehacha. So these are various
teachings of אמוראים, Amoraim, but the תנא tanna learns it out from
the following verse.
Which תנא? tanna?
The תנא tanna we're about to quote, not our תנא. tanna. דתניא,
detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, beraisa, רבי חייא אומר, Rabbi Chiya
omer, Rabbi Chiya says, מנין לשחיטה מן הצואר? minayin l'shechitah min hatzavar?
How do you know שחיטה shechitah is from the neck or the
throat? שנאמר, shene'emar, וערכו בני אהרן הכהנים את הנתחים את הראש ואת
הפדר. ve'archu benei Aharon hakohanim et hanetachim et harosh ve'et hapader.
This talks about an עולה, olah, it says you slaughter it and
then you chop it up into pieces, and it says you put
the pieces and the head with the fat around the with the
head on the fire. So why did it say the head separate
from the pieces? The head is one of the pieces. So את
הראש ואת
הפדר. et harosh ve'et hapader. מה תלמוד לומר את הראש ואת הפדר?
mah talmud lomar et harosh ve'et hapader? Why did it say the
head and the fat? והלא הראש
והפדר בכלל כל הנתחים היו? vehalo harosh vehapader bichlal kol hanetachim hayu?
Wasn't the head and the fat part of all the pieces? I
don't know about fat, but at least the head was part of
one of the pieces of the animal, and if you put you
know you sever it into pieces and you put them on the
fire, why mention the head separate? So למה יצאו? lamah yatze'u? Why
were they singled out? לפי שנאמר, lefi shene'emar, because the verse said
when it talks about cutting it into pieces, והפשיט את העולה, vehifshit
et ha'olah, you should flay, remove the skin of the עולה, olah,
ונתח אותה לנתחיה, veniteach otah lenetache'ah, and you shall cut it up
into pieces. אין לי אלא נתחים שישנם בכלל הפשטה, ein li ela
netachim sheyeshnam bichlal hafshatah,
so I only know that you cut it up into pieces on
the part of the animal that you flay. So מנין לרבות את
הראש שכבר הותז? minayin lerabbot et harosh shekvar hutaz? How do I
know you you have to also put the head which was not
severed with the rest of the animal? Why? Because what he's saying
is like this. תורה Torah describes a process. Here's the process: slaughter
the עולה, olah, flay it, and then cut it up into pieces.
So,
you are not doing the second part of that, flaying and cutting
into pieces with the head, because the head after you שחט'ד shachted
is already severed and already a separate piece. So if you're doing
a flaying and a severing, one process on on what you have
in front of you, it's on the carcass, it's not on the
head which has already been severed. So the carcass is now what
is being flayed and severed. So that's what I know, and by
the way, the head is put up without being flayed. You put
up the head with the skin. Probably be a pretty difficult job
to remove the skin from the head. Anyway, okay. So now I
know you do a process of flaying and severing by the pieces.
So when the תורה Torah says put the pieces on the fire,
maybe it only refers to the pieces that were part of that
process of flaying and severing. Maybe it doesn't refer to the head
which was severed in a different process, in the process of שחיטה.
shechitah's Maybe that's not considered, maybe that's not considered one of the
pieces that's put on the fire. One minute. So you don't we
don't know. We're assuming that it was severed in שחיטה. shechitah. We're
not learning that, but you'll see. Okay, hold on. So, מכלל דשחיטה
מן הצואר? michlal deshchitah min hatzavar? So therefore it says, תלמוד לומר,
talmud lomar, the verse says, את ראשו ואת פדרו, et rosho ve'et
pidro, the head and the fat, וערך, ve'arach, and put it on
the fire. And therefore you know that even though the head was
not part of the same process, it still gets put on the
fire. So the גמרא Gemara says, מכדי קאמר, michdi ka'amar, so we're
going to learn something not from what, you know, the verse is
saying, but the assumption essentially that we bring in to the verse.
So מכדי קאמר, michdi ka'amar, since this is saying את הראש שכבר
הותז, et harosh shekvar hutaz, how do I know to include the
head that's already been, you know, severed, מכלל דשחיטה מן הצואר, michlal
deshchitah min hatzavar, obviously שחיטה shechitah is from the neck. From where
you're שחיטה shchita from the neck. Now this might be a perfect
example of circular reasoning, right? You come with an assumption, you read
your assumption into the verses, and then in the end you come
back having you know learning your assumption from the verses. So I'm
coming with an assumption that you do the שחיטה shchita from the
head. I say okay so the verse is based on this you
know how do I know that you know maybe the head wouldn't
get put on the מזבח? mizbeach? Oh but it says you do
the... oh look the verses are telling me you do שחיטה shchita
from the head. They didn't really tell you that. That was the
assumption you brought to them. But the way to... it's not... but
so yes, you could say it's circular but it's not really because
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is like this. Start the other
way. Why would the פסוק pasuk have to tell me put the
head on the fire separate from the other parts of the animal?
The only way to understand this is if we assume you did
the שחיטה shchita from the head. The head was separate already and
therefore it conceptually would not have been part of the of the
practice of the dismembering. But if the שחיטה shchita were not from
the head, right, so then there would be no reason the תורה
Torah would treat the head separately. So it really is not circular.
Yes, in the way it's presented there's a... it's presented with the
assumption that the שחיטה's shchita from the head but you can also
derive it. The only explanation of why the תורה Torah would single
out the head is if the head was not dismembered with the
rest of the animal. And the only way the head would not
be dismembered with the rest of the animal is if it was
already dismembered because it was part of the act of שחיטה.
shchita Right, that context we were saying before, לשון וגיסטרא. lashon vegistera.
Ah, so that's part of the problem and רש"י Rashi notes this
that it not real... it is not dismembered, right, it is not
completely cut through, it's only the two סימנים. simanim. But רש"י Rashi
says okay but at least the fact that it is detached to
that degree is enough to consider it already dismembered. Okay, which now
you could say that weakens the whole דרשה. drashah. Okay, but nevertheless
the point is the פסוקים psukim single out head. The only way
to understand singling out head and why they're not treated as the
rest of the animal is to understand that to some degree the
head was already severed, maybe not fully severed but to some degree
it was already severed. So it's actually not a bad דרשה. drashah.
It does seem to suggest that the head was you know treated
separately.
Yes, and maybe this is reminiscent of what you said about cutting
the backbone.
Yes,
so that's what רש"י Rashi says that when it says הותז hutaz
severed it does not literally mean severed, it means mostly detached, that's
true. But again the point is is that the only way to
explain why the פסוקים psukim are treating the head separately is if
we assume that to some degree the head was cut off, maybe
not fully cut off but to some degree cut off. Okay, so
now the גמרא's Gemara just going to go back and analyze this
דרשה. drashah. So
the גמרא Gemara says like
this, והתנא פתח בראש ופדר ומסיים בראשו ופדרו, Vehatanna patach berosh upader
umesayem berosho ufidero, right, so now just a very technical point. It
started saying why do I need the verse to say the head
and the fat and that was one verse. And then it turns
in the end to say that's why it says its head and
its fat, which is a different verse. So which verse are you
learning it from? Why did he quote a different verse at the
end than it opened with the beginning? הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, this
is what it means. מניין לרבות את הראש שכבר הותז, Minyayin lerabbot
et harosh shekvar hutaz, so how do we know that the head
which is already cut at the time of שחיטה shchita that even
that is put on the fire? תלמוד לומר את הראש ואת הפדר,
Talmud lomar et harosh ve'et hapader, the head and the fat, that's
what the first verse we opened with. And now we have another
verse about head and fat. הראש ופדרו למה לי, Harosh ufidero lamma
li, now the second verse that says its head its fat, what
do I do with that second verse? מיבעי ליה לכדתניא, Miba'ei lei
lekhidetanya, to teach me what we taught in a ברייתא. beraita. מניין
לראש ופדר שקודמין לכל הנתחים, Minyayin lerosh upader shekodmin lekhol hannetachim,
how do you know that the head and the fat are put
first on the fire? That they're the first thing put on the
fire? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, so it says את ראשו ואת פדרו
וערך, Et rosho ve'et pidero ve'arach, based on the juxtaposition. Its head,
its fat, and you shall put. So the first time it uses
the word וערך ve'arach to lay it on the fire it's juxtaposed
to the head and the fat. So you learn a different thing.
Now head and fat are singled out for two reasons. There's two
times it says it. Once it's singled out to tell you although
it's not dismembered with together with the rest of the animal it
still goes on the fire and the other time it's singled out
is to tell you it goes first on the fire. Now why
does it say fat? Right, that'll explain why it says head, but
why does it say fat? ופדר למה לי, Upader lamma li, okay
good, ופדר למה לי, upader lamma li,
and why did it say fat in the first verse? מיבעי ליה
לכדתניא, Miba'ei lei lekhidetanya, like we taught in a ברייתא. beraita. כיצד
הוא עושה, Keitzad hu oseh, how do you put the head on
the fire? חופה את הפדר על בית השחיטה ומעלהו. Chofeh et hapader
al beit hashechitah uma'alehu.
It's not like nice to have the place where it's severed and
the exposed, you know, inside, all you have to do is look
at that very graphic picture, like yuck, that doesn't look so nice
to put on the fire. So what you do is you cover
the place of the severing with the fat. So it says, you're
right, the emphasis is to tell you number one the head although
severed separately is put on the fire, number two it's put on
the fire first, but every time it mentions head it mentions fat
to tell you here's how you put the head on the fire,
you use the fat to cover the place of the cut so
that it looks nice.
You give it a nice look.
Right, exactly, well maybe you rinse the fat, I don't know, okay.
וזה דרך כבוד של מעלה, Vezeh derech kavod shel ma'alah, this is
a respectful way to put it up to give it to God.
Okay, so that is actually a nice דרשה, drashah, you know, it's
certainly more satisfying than the other ones which were all these weird
plays on words. It's saying look, the head is treated separately. Presumably
it means because it was already done.
So why didn't they, you were going to ask that,
why didn't they say that one and that one and that one?
Nope, I don't know, it's a good question. Although the one thing
you don't get from this דרשה drasha is which תוספות Tosfot tried
to say you were getting from the others, is how do you
know it's from the throat and not from the back of the
neck? That we weren't addressing. Okay. Now we're going to have another
דרשה. drasha. והאי תנא, Ve'hai tanna, the following תנא, tanna, מייתי לה
מהכא, meiti lah mehacha, learns it from here. דתניא, Detanya, זאת תורת
הבהמה והעוף. Zot torat habehema veha'of.
This is the law of the בהמה behema of animals and birds.
וכי באיזו תורה שוותה בהמה לעוף? Vechi be'eizo torah shavta behema le'of?
Now this is in the context of animals that cause טומאה, tuma,
that are the source of impurity. So the גמרא Gemara says, the
ברייתא braita says, where are mammals and birds ever similar in terms
of the way they impart impurity? They never do it in the
same way. Why? ועוף לבהמה. Ve'of lebehema. And where is a bird
similar to a mammal? בהמה, Behema, a dead corpse of an animal,
like of a, you know, a dead cow, מטמאה במגע ובמשא, metamei
bemaga uvemasa, causes טומאה tuma through touch or through carrying.
ועוף אינו מטמא במגע ובמשא. Ve'of eino metamei bemaga uvemasa. A dead
bird does not cause טומאה tuma through touch or carrying. Right, there's
a very special and weird way a bird causes טומאה. tuma. And
in the reverse?
בעוף מטמא בבגדים אבית הבליעה. Be'of metamei bevigadim aveit habli'a. How does
an עוף of cause טומאה? tuma? If you have a dead bird,
not
slaughtered, a נבילה, nevela, whatever, of a dead bird and you swallow
it, when it is in your gullet, when it is, you know,
down your esophagus, that's when it causes טומאה. tuma. When you swallow
the meat of a נבילה, nevela, of a bird that wasn't slaughtered
correctly. So it only causes טומאה tuma not through touch or carrying,
but through being swallowed. And what? If you hold it in your
mouth. If you hold it in your mouth, not, it has to
actually be swallowed, it has to be going down your
throat. Okay, I'm serious, right.
So, and
the reason it says מטמא בבגדים metamei bevigadim is it doesn't only
cause you to be טמא, tamei, it causes the clothes you're wearing
to be טמא tamei as well, with an equal level of טומאה,
tuma, a ראשון. rishon. Okay, so that's how a bird causes טומאה,
tuma, but not an animal. ובהמה אינה מטמאה בבגדים אבית הבליעה, Uvehema
einah metama bevigadim aveit habli'a, but not an animal. Now of course
you could say, well I don't get it, if I'm swallowing the
meat of a corpse of an animal, I'm also touching it, I'm
lifting it up. Okay, but it says, let's say your friend comes
and he sticks, you know,
a hamburger, he feeds you into your throat and that, right, exactly.
Anyway, you would not be טמא. tamei. So the טומאה tuma of
an animal is not like a bird, of a bird is not
like an animal. So why does the תורה Torah say that here
is the law of the bird and the animal?
Okay, so באיזו תורה שוותה בהמה לעוף ואוף לבהמה? Be'eizo torah shavta
behema le'of ve'of lebehema? In what way is a mammal similar to
a bird and a bird to a mammal? In the context of
טומאה tuma or in any context? לומר לך, Lomar lach, to tell
you, מה בהמה בשחיטה אף עוף בשחיטה. mah behema bishchita af of
bishchita.
So the same way you do a שחיטה shchita, by a mammal,
you do it by a bird. Now where do you know you
do שחיטה shchita. from a mammal? So רש"י Rashi says, oh, well
we'll have to assume like one of the earlier דרשות drashot that
we just got through with. Either the whole idea from the עולה,
olah, or from the idea by what do you call it, you
know, וזבחת, vezavachta, whatever. So if that's true, this is not a
new source of how you know you do שחיטה Shechitah by the
neck. Right? Because it's based on the others. So the new source
is going to be the next opinion. This opinion assumes from some
other דרשה drasha or from tradition, we know you do שחיטה Shechitah
by the animal, mammal, but we don't know by the bird. If
you remember, there's a whole question about how clear it is that
you do שחיטה Shechitah by birds. So the reason the תורה Torah
here connects mammals to birds, it's to tell you yes, you have
whatever those weird דרשות drashot are before, but those are all by
mammals. How do you know you do שחיטה Shechitah by birds? That's
because this verse connects them. And that, by the way, it's being
connected also in the context of טומאה, tuma, because a way in
which an animal corpse does not become טמא tamei is if it
is slaughtered properly. So in this way birds and animals are the
same, that their corpse does not communicate טומאה tuma if they are
slaughtered properly. And we learn here is that the same way you
do שחיטה Shechitah by an animal, a mammal, you do it by
a bird.
And what is this verse say, what the תורה Torah means is
they just, however it is that they impart טומאה. tuma. All right.
Obviously, Michael, we're trying to make a דרשה. drasha. Okay. אם על
הלן ברוב שניים אף כאן ברוב שניים. Im al hallan berov shenayim
af kan berov shenayim. Now, maybe let's make it completely the same.
The same way for a mammal you have to cut both סימנים,
simanim, trachea and esophagus, maybe here too both סימנים. simanim. תלמוד לומר,
Talmud lomar, זאת, zot,
this, which means it's limited. It's not the same in all respects,
it's only the same in one respect. So שחיטה Shechitah, is required,
but not fully the same. That's the first דרשה drasha that doesn't
tell us the idea of שחיטה, Shechitah. it just applies it to
birds. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, now רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
is going to tell us a new source of the idea of
שחיטה. shechita. באיזו תורה שוותה בהמה לעוף ואוף לבהמה? Be'eizo torah shavta
behema le'of ve'of lebehema?
Again, raising this question, in what way is a בהמה behema similar
to a bird and a bird to a בהמה? behema? לומר לך,
Lomar lach, to tell you, מה עוף הכשרו מן הצוואר אף בהמה
הכשרה מן הצוואר. mah of hechshero min hatzavar af behema hechsherah min
hatzavar.
The same way birds you do from the neck, animals you do
from the neck. Where do you do birds from the neck? Anybody?
Michael? מליקה, Melika, right! Oh, David you got it. מליקה, Melika, right,
with the finger. So there the תורה Torah said explicitly, actually the
one place the תורה Torah explicitly describes a ritual act of slaughter
is by birds as קרבנות. korbanot. It says ומלק אתו ממול ערפו,
umalak oto mimul orpo, you should sort of sever whatever the word
מליקה melika means from the back of its neck. That is the
one place the תורה Torah explicitly explicitly describe some act of slaughter.
Okay, now true, it's a קרבן, Korban, it wouldn't be valid in
any other context, but here's a very nice דרשה. Drasha. Let's use
that as the model, and the same way birds are done from
the neck, any type of שחיטה shechita is done from the neck.
Maybe it's different, maybe it's from the front and not from the
back or whatever, but at least we can make the analogy and
say it's done from the neck. And that's what this, no, that's
what the connection
to the animal from the front of the neck
because if you're just going to say, yeah, so you could still
say that, right? We learn from those other פסוקים Pesukim front rather
than back or whatever, but here's where we learn the basic idea
of neck and because it connects it to bird and that's a
nice דרשה Drasha because that actually the תורה Torah specifically. So מה
העוף מן הצואר ma ha'of min hatzavar the same way a bird
you do the neck, אף בהמה מן הצואר af behemah min hatzavar
animals also from the neck. מה להלן ממול עורף אף כאן ממול
עורף, ma lehallan mimul oreph af kan mimul oreph, right? Maybe the
same way there's from the back of the neck here too it's
from the back of the neck. תלמוד לומר ומלק את ראשו ממול
ערפו ולא יבדיל Talmud lomar u'malak et rosho mimul orpo v'lo yavdil
you should,
you should do מליקה Melikah to its head, the possessive, from the
back of its neck and don't sever. ראשו של זה ממול עורף
Rosho shel zeh mimul oreph this head gets cut off from the
back of the neck, ולא ואין ראשו של אחר ממול עורף v'lo
v'ein rosho shel acher mimul oreph this
other heads you do not sever them from the back of the
neck, you sever them from the throat. Okay, so maybe you don't
even need the other דרשה Drasha because it says no, there's a
way in which the bird, the only the bird is the back
of the neck. So actually this is quite a lovely דרשה Drasha
because you know you actually had doing the one place the תורה
Torah really does specifically describe the act and it's from the the
neck, admittedly the back of the neck, but at least from there
we can learn out that other forms of שחיטה shechita. also are
basically at the...
Well only because there's תורת בהמה Torat behemah or whatever it is
which
is by טומאה Tumah though. I understand but to say you know
טומאה Tumah has or the שחיטה shechita? has relevance to טומאה. Tumah.
Look if you don't and even if you don't like the specific
פסוק Pasuk it's hinging it on, again by analogy it's reasonable to
understand that the שחיטה shechita? of other things would be at least
somewhat similar to what's done by the bird and at least take
place at the neck.
I don't understand why we can't just say
it's all הלכה למשה מסיני. Halachah l'Moshe m'Sinai. Well we more or
less are saying, I mean a lot of the דרשות, Drashot, גמרא,
Gemara it's a tradition, but to some degree we'd like to link
some of it to פסוקים. Pesukim. Okay, look let's face it שחיטה
shechita, is the most, you know the whole laws of שחיטה, shechita,
it's not only the details are absent which you have in a
lot of areas, it's that the the תורה Torah has never explicitly
said you cannot eat an animal that's not שחט properly, there's a
ritual of שחיטה. shechita. Most cases the תורה שבעל פה Torah she-Ba'al
Peh fills up the details. Right, don't do מלאכה Melachah on שבת.
Shabbat. What's מלאכה? Melachah? Right? You know
so it could be anything. So it fills out a million details.
But at least it says don't do מלאכה. Melachah. Right? It does
say don't eat a נבלה. nevelah. Right? But it never says oh
if the way something is not a נבלה nevelah is that there's
this thing called ritual slaughter that you have to do. It never
says that, right? So even the concept of ritual slaughter is not
so clear in the תורה. Torah. So it's not so bad that
the גמרא Gemara is not just saying it's all הלכה למשה מסיני,
Halachah l'Moshe m'Sinai, I want to link some of it to פסוקים.
Pesukim.
Same we say you know gets into why it's so opaque.
No, I don't know.
Back to the question. Yes. Should touching a mammal
carcass? Yes.
Correct, correct. Unless you carry. If you do טומאת משא Tumat Massa
it makes your טומאה Tumah a ראשון.
Rishon. Okay. Say you'd say מגע maga makes just you.
You a ראשון Rishon and then by your clothes touching you your
clothes are a שני.
Sheni. טומאת משא Tumat Massa makes both you and the... But with
the bird it's both the same right away, no matter what.
Correct. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. Okay, ורבי אליעזר
האי זאת מאי עביד ליה? v'Rabbi Eliezer hai zot mai avid lei?
What does Rabbi Eliezer do with the פסוק Pasuk זאת? zot? Which
means that the equation is not complete. So אי לאו זאת ei
lav zot were it not for זאת, zot, הוה אמינא מה עוף
בסימן אחד אף בהמה בסימן אחד. hava amina mah of b'siman echad
af behemah b'siman echad. Same point except the reverse. The same way
reverse we said don't require two סימנים Simanim by birds because we
were applying what we knew from animals to birds, here we're going
the reverse. We're applying from birds to animals. So from birds to
animals we apply the idea of the neck, but don't maybe I
should say oh bird only requires one סימן, siman. maybe an animal
only one סימן. siman כתב רחמנא זאת katav Rachmana zot don't make
the complete complete equation. Bird is one סימן siman, but an animal
is two.
I didn't know that way not a different way then?
I don't know. תני בר קפרא. Tani Bar Kappara. Now we are
done with how we know the idea of throat or neck, and
now we get to this issue about birds versus animals, two סימנים
Simanim versus one סימן, siman? which we've been assuming but it has
yet to be spelled out, right? תורה Torah has yet to say
two סימנים Simanim by בהמה. behemah. At most we know is throat.
We don't know two סימנים. Simanim. And how do we know that
an a bird is one סימן? siman. None of that we know.
So now let's take a look. תני בר קפרא, Tani Bar Kappara,
so Bar Kappara taught, זאת תורת הבהמה והעוף. Zot Torat ha-Behemah ve-ha-Of.
This is the law of the בהמה Behemah and the bird. And
the end of the פסוק Pasuk says ובכל נפש החיה הרמשת במים,
u-ve-chol nefesh ha-chayah ha-romeset ba-mayim, and all living creatures in the water.
So it lists three things: mammals, birds, fish. So within that spectrum
here's what we're going to say. היטל
הכתוב לעוף בין בהמה לדגים. Heitel ha-katuv l'of bein behemah l'dagim. It
puts birds between mammals and fish.
לחייבו בשני סימנים
אי אפשר.
L'chayvo b'shnei simanim i efshar.
To say that
a bird has you have to cut...
To say that a bird has to—you have to cut both סימנים
simanim like a בהמה—how behemah we know בהמה behemah we don't know,
but okay—like a בהמה, behemah, that you can't say, שכבר הוקש לדגים,
shekevar hukash ledagim, because on the one side it's connected to fish,
and fish you don't have to do any formal שחיטה. shechita We'll
talk about that in a minute. So לפוטרו בלא כלום, liftoro belo
kelum,
to say it doesn't have to require any שחיטה shechita by birds,
אי אפשר, ee efshar, that you can't say, שכבר הוקש לבהמה, shekevar
hukash lebehemah, cause on the other side it's connected to a mammal.
So הא כיצד? ha keitzad? So what does it require? הכשירו בסימן
אחד. hechshiro besiman echad.
It's smack in the middle, there's a spectrum. Mammal is two, birds
are zero—I mean not birds, fish are zero—so what are birds going
to be? Birds are going to be one. Okay, that's a very
nice דרשה, drasha, but hey, how do you know birds—fish are zero?
And how do you know mammals are two? So let's take a
look.
Fish are zero, fish you can kill—you don't have to even cut.
Well, right. Well, that's what zero is. There's no act of שחיטה.
shechita You can cut them without cutting.
Okay, that's true. Okay, so let's take a look. So
okay, so the גמרא Gemara is going to say, הא כיצד, ha
keitzad, בסימן אחד. besiman echad. דגים דלאו בני שחיטה נינהו מנלן? dagim
delav bnei shechita ninhu minalan? How do you know fish do not
require any act of שחיטה? shechita אי לימא משום דכתיב, ee leima
mishum deketiv, because the verse says—when, you know, בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael
are complaining to משה Moshe and then משה Moshe and God says
I'm going to give them meat and then משה Moshe says to
God: הצאן ובקר ישחט להם ואם את כל דגי הים יאסף להם
ומצא להם? hatzon uvakar yishachet lahem ve'im et kol degei hayam ye'aseif
lahem umatza lahem? He says,
even if you, you know, slaughter all of the, you know, cattle
and all of the flocks and you slaughter for them, and you
gather all of the fish, will it ever be enough for these
people? So look at the comparison, the parallel: slaughter the cattle and
the flock, and gather the fish. But by—mammals they have to be
slaughtered. What? And birds aren't mentioned? Right, that's the point. We don't
have to worry about them. Whatever, they're not relevant right now. So
you see, באסיפה בעלמא סגי להו, ba'asifa be'alma sagi lehu, so you
see they don't need to be slaughtered, you just gather them. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אלא מעתה גבי שליו דכתיב, ella me'atah gabbei
slav deketiv, one minute, you can't say the word gather just doesn't
mean require slaughter, because when it comes to the שליו slav it
says, ויאספו את השליו, vaya'asfu et haslav,
they gathered the quail. So הכי נמי דלאו בשחיטה, hachi nami delav
beshechita, would you say that quail does not require שחיטה? shechita ואמרת
לפוטרו בלא כלום אי אפשר, ve'amart liftoro belo kelum ee efshar, you
said that you can't exempt birds without an act of שחיטה, shechitah.
שכבר הוקש לבהמה, shekevar hukash lebehemah, it's linked to בהמה. behemah. So
the גמרא Gemara says, no, no, no, there's a big difference. התם
לא כתיב אסיפה
במקום שחיטה דאחריני, hatam lo ketiv asifa bemakom shechita dachrini, the word
gather is not parallel to a word slaughter, it just says gather,
so gather doesn't mean don't do שחיטה, shechitah gather means gather when
it's coming on its own. To find, gather the quail. דאחריני, dachrini,
it's not compared to slaughter by other things. הכא כתיב אסיפה במקום
שחיטה דאחריני, hacha ketiv asifa bemakom shechita dachrini,
here there's a parallel, it says slaughtering cattle and flock and gather
fish, so the gathering of fish is equal to the slaughtering of
cattle and flock. You don't need to do any formal שחיטה. shechita
Now, some people try to be cute, obviously the simple sense of
the גמרא Gemara is fish require absolutely no שחיטה at all. Some
people try to be cute and try to say that, oh, maybe
what the גמרא Gemara, is saying is אסיפה, asifa, the form of
שחיטה by fish is that you actually take them out of the—you
know—out of the water. So just to show you how people in
ישיבה Yeshiva don't have enough time on their hands, they ask the
question, what would be if you were to eat a fish in
the water without ever having, you know, fished it out of the
water? Would that be okay or not? Does it require some act
and the act is אסיפה, asifa, gathering out of the water, or
not at all? Obviously the simple sense of the גמרא is לאו
בני שחיטה, lav bnei shechita, there's no concept of שחיטה by fish
altogether. What? Is there אבר מן החי?
eiver min hachai? No.
You know,
right now in Japan, right, they have this type—some people sushi isn't
enough, so the most fancy thing is to eat actually some form
of live fish. Do you know about this? Like you take some
type of a fish worm or whatever and you swallow it and
you feel it, you know, squiggle as it goes down your throat,
it's considered to be a delicacy. So anyway, that actually would—if it's
a כשר kosher fish,
if
it were a כשר kosher fish, that actually would be הלכה halakhically
acceptable. There is no—there is no שחיטה by fish.
I've seen it in Korean restaurants where they have a long fish,
and the fish's gills are still breathing, and they eat—they eat from
the fish. Right.
It's a college hazing ritual also where they swallow it whole.
They swallow it whole, they eat from the fish. They eat from
the fish, they cut pieces from the fish.
While the fish is still alive?
While the fish is breathing.
I don't know if—ah, that's—that's interesting. That would be another example. The
fish itself could still be in the water and you chop off
a piece of the fish. Right. So if you want to take
the word אסיפה asifa literally here, then you would have to remove
it from the water, but the simple sense of the גמרא is
unquestionably that there's no concept of שחיטה by fish.
We do it somewhere else?
What, is there אבר מן החי eiver min hachai from fish? Correct.
Correct.
And the שליו? slav? Yes, this is the first time that I'm
imagining that the שליו slav was alive when it came in the
desert. I didn't think it came in cellophane.
Yeah,
it's an interesting point. You know, I always—I always imagined that, you
know, they were like totally, you know, you could grab them out
of the air, but that they were still—you know—it's sort of like
when you have—you hear about—when you hear about these plagues of locusts,
right, fried chicken came with שליו?
slav? Fried chicken came from the sky?
No, no, no, you know when people actually, you know in these
places where there are these like swarms of locusts and they eat
locusts, they talk about like grabbing locusts from the air and eating
them. Yeah.
So it was like מן, Mann, you know, that was lying on
the ground, the שלו Slav is lying on the ground.
Oh, that's interesting. Well it does say חמרים חמרים. chamarim chamarim. It
says, what it say, what doesn't it say, you know, ויגז את
השלו? vayagez es haslav? Yeah, so he says that it
says וינח מחוץ למחנה, vayaniach michutz lamachaneh, is that the פסוק? pasuk?
No, but
even, even, even, yeah, yeah, so
you might be right.
You know, but it doesn't mean, I guess the question is, was
whether they were alive or dead.
הבשר עודנו בין שניהם טרם יכרת. Habasar odenu bein shineihem terem yikares.
So what does it mean? It doesn't say whether it was alive
or dead.
הבשר עודנו בין שניהם טרם יכרת. Habasar odenu bein shineihem terem yikares.
Yeah, which sounds to me like they were eating it.
They hadn't finished chewing the meat.
No, or you could say טרם יכרת terem yikares means before the
thing
was actually killed, before the, meaning they're eating אבר מן החי. ever
min hachai.
I don't know why, oh hold on. טרם יכרת, Terem yikares, it
says cutting off, cutting off.
I
understand, I'm just saying that I never... okay. ורוח נסע מאת השם
ויגז שלוים ויטש על המחנה כדרך יום כה וכדרך יום כה סביבות
המחנה וכאמתים על פני הארץ. Veruach nasa me-eis Hashem vayagez slavim vayitosh
al hamachaneh kederech yom ko uchederech yom ko sevivot hamachaneh uche-amatayim al
penei ha'aretz. Right.
And so it says it's, it's sort of, it gathered it and
it's deposited it. And it does speak about it being piled on
the ground, and they went and they gathered it. Right. וישטחו להם
שטוח סביב. Vayishtechu lahem shatoach saviv. Yeah,
so it does sound obviously like it was piled on the ground.
I guess the question is piled and they were piled on one
another alive or piled and they were already dead. Okay,
alright,
so let's continue. Okay, but of course, but what we don't have
here... all
right, but what we don't have here is, we don't have here,
so we have דגים dagim gets zero, we have this continuum, so
birds get one, what we don't ever have explicit, which in the
end the גמרא's going to say tomorrow is also a tradition, is
that how do you know the mammals get two? To work out
the whole continuum, you needed the other end of the continuum and
that we have yet to say. Okay, let's take a look, but
now
we're going to continue in this idea though about the difference between
birds and mammals. דרש עובר גלילאה. Darash over Gelila'ah. So an itinerant
Galilean דרשן. darshan. Actually it's quite interesting that phrase עובר גלילאה, over
Gelila'ah, they had this idea of itinerant rabbis that would go around
and, you know, give sermons, give דרשות. drashot. Okay, so עובר גלילאה
over Gelila'ah means a Galilean rabbi who was עובר, over, he was
a transient itinerant rabbi. Okay, דרשן. darshan. So he made the following
דרשה. drasha. We don't even know his name. בהמה שנבראת מן היבשה,
Behemah shenivres min hayabashah,
mammals that were created from the solid earth, terra firma, הכשירה בשני
סימנים. hechshirah bishnei simanim. You need to cut both סימנים simanim because
they apparently, you know, they're more stable, they have more life to
them, you need to cut both סימנים. simanim. דגים שנברו מן המים,
Dagim shenivru min hamayim,
fish that are from the water are very like, you know, nonsubstantial,
הכשירן בלא כלום. hechshiran belo klum.
Don't require any form to anything to make them kosher, you know,
to make them edible, בלא כלום. belo klum. עוף שנברא מן הרקק,
Of shenivra min harakak,
birds that are created from the muddy swamp, a mixture of dirt
and water. So they're, you know, not as stable as mammals but
not as totally, you know, non-stable like birds? So they are הכשירה
בסימן אחד, hechshirah besiman echad, you do a middle amount, you cut
one סימן. Siman, סימן, siman what does it mean birds are made
from the mud? We'll see in a minute. אמר רב שמואל קפוטקאה,
Amar Rav Shmuel Kaputka'ah, or Shmuel from Kaputka says, תדע שהרי עופות
יש בהם קשקשת ברגליהם כדגים. teida sheharei ofos yesh bahem kaskeses beragleihem
kedagim. I will show you a sort of still a vestige of
the fact that birds were created from the mud, from this mixture
of earth and
water,
birds have a type of scales on their legs like fish. Is
this true? Go look at a chicken.
It has
like scaly type of things by the feet? Sure. Okay, fine. I'll
take your word for it. Okay, so now we're going to look
at where this idea is that birds were created from the... what
do you call it? From the mud. I will say by the
way, another interesting thing to note, like we noted on the first
page, which is the emphasis on blood, although that's not technically שחיטה.
You know, the esophagus, please correct me if I'm wrong because my
medical knowledge is limited. You can cut the esophagus and still live,
right? I mean the esophagus, I mean if you're fed intravenously, right?
I mean is that true? I mean will a cut esophagus lead
to death?
They skip over tracheotomy, they breathe through a hole in their neck.
Well that's true also. But I'm just saying the esophagus... okay, a
cut esophagus, if it leads to death, it only leads to death
through a very elongated process of starving to death, right? As opposed
to a trachea, which immediately basically makes a person, you know, asphyxiate,
correct? So I do think it's interesting that the גמרא understands that
the idea of cutting both סימנים, simanim, and we had this before,
that the idea of שחיטה is connected to the idea of, you
know, killing, and the more something is alive and a substantial life
like an animal, a mammal, the more you have to cut both
סימנים simanim because it just seems to me, you know, that it's
again, it's the continuum. It’s not so clear to me how the
esophagus, cutting the esophagus is about immediately killing the animal. If it
impacts the life of the animal, it’s only if you wait like
three days for the animal to starve to death. So oh yeah,
very nice. Okay, here’s chicken legs that have like little bumps and
ridges or whatever look a little bit like the etc. Anyway, I
just point that out and also by the way birds, think about
this point, you can שחט a bird by cutting just the esophagus.
If you cut just the esophagus and not the trachea, then this
bird is still breathing, the blood is still pumping, it’s just not
going to be able to eat, right, it’ll just eventually starve to
death. So again the connection between שחיטה and killing in my mind
is not always exactly clearly. But again the גמרא here assumes that
an animal that has more substantial life like a mammal you need
to cut more things. You cut two סימנים. simanim. Okay, so let’s
take a look at where we get this idea of the mud.
But wait,
Rabbi Yehuda comes in and says you essentially...
I understand, but still he’s not disagreeing on the one and the
two סימנים. simanim.
So why do you think that, why do you think that reflects
knowledge of biology versus primitive anatomical knowledge?
Oh well, that could be. You mean that the גמרא assumption of
identifying it with life is because of their, you know, maybe that’s
what they didn’t know more beyond that. That could be, that could
very well be. Although of course it’s going to be interesting because
we’re going to discuss tomorrow, you know, that there’s different טרפות, treifot,
what constitutes a טרפה treifa is different for the trachea and the
esophagus and so on. And it does sort of seem, I mean,
they could have had some tradition, but it does sort of seem
that they, you know, at least had some specificity.
Right, that’s Rabbi Tendler’s basis for his position on brain death. That
what? That there
was limited scientific knowledge.
Right, right, right, right.
Okay, so
that, that is true. But I’m saying so you’re right. I mean,
I’m not being fair by reading in our knowledge of the exact
function of these into, right, the way the גמרא connects them to
life. So that’s a very good point. Okay, point taken. Let’s take
a look now at the idea of the birds from the mud
and we’ll end with that. ועוד שאלו, Va'od sha'alo, he asked him.
Now who’s asked who? So there was this, there was this you
know Roman general or whatever, his name was קונטריקוס, Kuntriko, who asked
רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai a series of questions.
And that’s recorded in another גמרא, this is one of the questions
that’s relevant for us. He asked as well the following question: כתוב
אחד אומר, Katuv echad omer, one verse says, ויאמר אלהים ישרצו המים
שרץ נפש חיה ועוף יעופף. Vayomer Elokim yishretzu hamayim sheretz nefesh chaya
v'of yofef. God said let the water teem with life and birds,
right, so there that is the creation of the birds and they
are coming from on the fifth day, thank you, on the fifth
day and they are coming from the water. Let the water teem
with life, נפש חיה ועוף, nefesh chaya v'of, and birds flying on
the ground. אלמא ממיא איברי, Alma mimaya ivre, you see they are
created from the water. וכתיב, U'chtiv, the other verse says, ויצר יהוה
אלהים מן האדמה כל חית השדה ואת כל עוף השמים. Vayitzer Hashem
Elokim min ha'adama kol chayat hasadeh v'et kol of hashamayim.
Then it says in פרק ב perek bet of בראשית, Bereishit, which
is of course a different narrative, but it says there God created
from the ground all of the animals and all of the birds.
So פרק א perek aleph says the birds are in the water
and פרק ב perek bet says the birds are from the ground.
So how do you resolve it? אמר לו, Amar lo, he sent
back to him, מן הרקק נבראו, min harakak nivre, okay, they were
made from mud. ראה תלמידיו מסתכלין זה בזה, Ra'a talmidav mistaklin zeh
bazeh, he looked,
he saw his students like looking at one another astounded, like what
type of answer was that? אמר להם, Amar lahem, he said to
them, קשה בעיניכם שדחיתי את אויבי בקנה? kasha b'eineichem shedachiti et oyvi
b'kaneh? Is it difficult to you that I responded to my enemy
or we might say my antagonist or whatever, right, you know with
like with a reed, meaning I gave him a nonsense answer, a
straw? מן המים נבראו, mina mayim nivre, I’ll tell you the real
answer. The real answer is they were created from water like it
says in the first narrative in פרק א perek aleph בראשית. Bereishit.
ולמה הביאן אל האדם? Ve'lama hevi'an el ha'adam? The second narrative is
emphasizing that the animals were brought to man. So it’s not emphasizing
that the birds were created from the ground. It says he made
the animals from the ground and he brought the animals and the
bird and he brought everything to man, so it really wasn’t being
specific about how they were created. ולמה הביאן אל האדם,
V'lama
hevi'an
el ha'adam, why were they brought to man in the second פרק?
לקרוא להם שם, Likro lahem shem, to give them a name, which
really means the first פרק is detailing the process, the second פרק
is a narrative about man, it’s not a narrative about the animals
and it’s not being so specific about the animals. ויש אומרים, V'yesh
omrim, but of course that doesn’t get us to mud. We’re looking
for the mud, we want for our דרשה. drasha. So ויש אומרים,
V'yesh omrim, some say the reverse, בלשון אחר אמר לו לזו הגמון,
b'lashon acher amar lo l'zo Hagmon, he gave the second answer to
this הגמון, Hagmon, that that second narrative was not being specific. ובלשון
הראשון, U'v'lashon harishon, the first answer of mud, which is sort of
bringing the two together, אמר להם לתלמידיו. amar lahem l'talmidav. He said
to his students, משום דכתיב, mishum d'chtiv, that
that’s the real answer,
משום דכתיב על ויצר, mishum d'chtiv al vayitzer, because it says because
since it says that God created from the dirt, it sounds like
that the birds were part of the creation from the dirt in
the second narrative. So he didn’t want to say that they really
weren’t part of that creation. So yes, פרק א perek aleph says
water, פרק ב perek bet says dirt, they were created from mud
and that’s why they are not as substantial. So yes, פרק א
Perek Aleph says water, פרק ב Perek Bet says dirt. They were
created from mud and that's why they are not as substantial as
בהמה behema but not as insubstantial as fish and that's why you
cut one סימן but not two סימנים. simanim. Okay.